Claud D. Nelson Papers
Claud D. Nelson Papers
1845-1968
Nelson, Claud D.
3.8 linear ft.
Papers of the American Methodist minister, ecumenical leader (1889-1967). Collection contains correspondence (1907-1967); book manuscript, articles, book reviews, clippings, pamphlets; and memorabilia, including awards, photographs, and a scrapbook of sermons by Nelson's father and others.
149387
Biographical History
Claud Dalton Nelson (1889-1967) was an American Methodist minister and ecumenical leader. Born July 13, 1889 in Jacksonville, Arkansas, to Charley Heston Nelson and Sandra See Nelson, he received his bachelor's degree (and later an honorary LLD.) from Hendrix College. He studied at Oxford University as a Rhodes Scholar, receiving his M.A. from that institution. He was ordained a Methodist minister in the North Carolina Conference but never assumed a pastorate.
He worked for the YMCA from 1916-1951 and was Executive Director of the National Council of Churches' Department of Religious Liberty from 1953-1960, then worked as a reporter for the Religious News Service. He also served as editor of The Dialogue, a publication of the National Conference for Christians and Jews.
Nelson was married to the former Maud Sparks, with whom he had four sons.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Claud D. Nelson Papers contain correspondence, memorabilia, miscellanea, personal files, photographs, printed material, published material, and writings. Correspondence includes a letter from George Washington Carver (1932). Memorabilia contains a scrapbook of sermons by Nelson's father, as well as some he copied from other sources. The books in both published material and writings deal mainly with the Catholic Church and its concerns.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence and printed material are arranged chronologically. The remaining series are arranged alphabetically by type, author, or topic as appropriate.
Related Material
has numerous collections relating to church and clergy, and to the Methodist Church in particular. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Church and clergy; Religion and philosophy; Nelson, Claud D. -- Archives.; Clergy -- United States.; Clergy as authors.; Ecumenical movement.; Ecumenists -- United States.; Methodist Church -- Clergy.; Methodists -- United States.; Sermons, American.; Articles.; Awards.; Book reviews.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Sermons.; Authors.; Clergy.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - 1907-1946, 1950-1967, undated, 7 folders (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards, 1907-1947 (Box 1)
  - Certificates, 1913-1965 (Box 1)
  - Passports, 1910-1949 (Box 1)
  - Poster, 1930 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1945 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Lecture for Sherwood Eddy Group, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Films for lecture, 1935; 4 reels (Box 1)
- Personal files
  - Biographical material, 1936-1965 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Miscellaneous, 1930-1965 (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Books, 12 volumes (Box 1)
  - Books, 28 volumes (Box 2)
  - Books, 15 volumes (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1935-1968 (Box 3)
  - Magazines, 1961-1968 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1921-1967 (Box 3)
  - Pamphlets, 1928-1968; 2 folders (Box 3)
- Writings
  - Articles, 1935-1966 (Box 3)
  - Book reviews, 1927-1965 (Box 3)
  - Books
    - Church and State, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Implementing Vatican II in Your Community, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Religion and Society, 1966 (Box 4)
    - The Vatican Council and All Christians, 1962 (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1939-1962 (Box 4)
  - The Dialogue, 1961-1967; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Magazines, 1935-1966; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 1935-1961 (Box 5)
  - Notes (Box 5)
  - Pamphlets, 1937-1966 (Box 5)
  - Typescript, "Pilgrim of Rome" (Box 5)